Guide to the Thomas Francis Parkinson Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Thomas Francis Parkinson Papers,
1950-1985.
Parkinson, Thomas Francis, 1920-
1 linear ft. (2 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0974
4078533
The Thomas Parkinson Papers contain correspondence between Parkinson and members of the San Francisco literary scene, such as beat poets Allen Ginsberg, Michael McClure, Gary Snyder, and Philip Whalen. The collection also includes manuscripts written by Parkinson and his friends and associates.
Biographical Note
Thomas Parkinson was a professor of literature at the University of California Berkeley, a poet, political activist, and scholar of William Butler Yeats and the writers and culture of the Beat Generation.
Parkinson was born in San Francisco in 1920. He grew up in the Haight-Ashbury district with his father, a plumber and union leader. His father's political and union activities shaped Parkinson's own political views, and he remained a committed political activist throughout his life.
Parkinson graduated from Lowell High School and attended some courses at a junior college, but left to do odd jobs and a brief stint in the army before returning to the University of California Berkeley. He completed his Bachelor's, and then his PhD at Berkeley and stayed on to teach as faculty member in the English Department. He remained at Berkeley for the entirety of his career as a scholar, and was awarded the University's highest honor, the Berkeley Citation, in 1991.
In addition to his activities as a scholar, Parkinson was a poet who was involved in the art and literary scene in the San Francisco area in the 1950s and 1960s. He was friendly with poets such as Michael McClure, Gary Snyder, Philip Whalen, Robert Duncan, and Allen Ginsberg, and wrote an early academic analysis of beat poetry entitled A Casebook of the Beat in 1961.
Thomas Parkinson died of a heart attack in 1992, survived by his wife, the artist and theatrical designer Ariel Parkinson.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, and printed ephemera related to Thomas Parkinson and his involvement in the San Francisco Renaissance literary scene.
Arrangement
Material is arranged into two series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1950-1985
Series II: Manuscripts, 1957-1980
Subjects
Parkinson, Thomas Francis, 1920-; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Corso, Gregory.; McClure, Michael.; Snyder, Gary.; Whalen, Philip.; Bohemianism.; Beat generation.; Correspondence; Poets, American--20th century.; College teachers
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
10/16/87 M-87-10-16 Purchase, 400-10.16.87
08/16/88 M-88-08-16 Gary Snyder letters, manuscripts, and photographs. Serendipity Books Purchase-297-08.l6.88
Purchase, 1987; l988.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1950-1985
  The correspondence series is comprised of letters to and from Parkinson related to his involvement in the literary scene of the beat generation and the San Francisco Renaissance.
  - BBC to Ginsberg and Parkinson, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Corso, Gregory to Parkinson, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Feinberg, Charles to Parkinson, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ginsberg, Allen to Parkinson, undated, 1950-1985, (5 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 4 to 8)
  - McClure, Michael to Parkinson, undated and 1963-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Parkinson
    - to Allen Ginsberg, undated 1958-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - to Michael McClure, 1963-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - to Gary Snyder, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - to Philip Whalen, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Snyder, Gary (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - to Ariel Parkinson, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - to Parkinson, 1959-1983, (6 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 13 to 18)
      (some of these letters include poetry manuscripts)
  - Whalen, Philip to Parkinson, undated and 1957-1980, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 3)
- Series II: Manuscripts, 1957-1980
  The Manuscripts series includes manuscripts of poetry by Michael McClure, Gary Snyder, and Philip Whalen, as well as a collection of publishing announcements and gallery invitations for writers and artists associated with the San Francisco poetry scene. This series also includes a manuscript of Michael McClure's book of essays, Wolf Net, inscribed to Tom and his wife Ariel.
  - McClure, Michael
    - Ghost Tantra #31 (Box 15-H-03)
    - Notes and Poems, undated and 1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      (Also includes an essay on Allen Ginsberg's poetry)
    - Wolf Net typescript, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      (inscribed to Tom and Ariel Parkinson)
  - Snyder, Gary
    - Poetry Manuscripts, Resume, and Statement on Parkinson, 1965-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Whalen, Philip
    - Poetry, 1958-1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "O Tom, O Parkinson," 1961 (Box 15-H-03)
      (poem dedicated to Parkinson)
  - Printed Material (Box 2, Folder 9)
    (Advertisements, Announcements, and Clippings)